thank you
John kiriako well with me today a former
CIA official who blew the whistle on the
agency's torture practices after 9 11
John kiriako served as the chief of
counterterrorist operations in Pakistan
Mr kirako was reportedly praised at the
agency for his role in the capture of
Abu zubaidah who back in 2002 was
thought to be Al qaeda's third in
commend and now years later John kiriako
is heading to prison he was just
sentenced to two and a half years in
jail Mr kiriaku thank you so much for
coming thanks for having me I really
appreciate it I know that time is of
much value to you and your family now
before you
find yourself behind bars
you were convicted of revealing the
identity of an agent to a freelance
reporter who by the way never even
published it you said you regretted
sharing the name of the agent of the
officer that you apologized for it but
you also said it was not why the
government
went after you why do you think
the government went after you I've I
have never believed that my case was
about a leak I have always believed that
my case is about torture
when I went on uh ABC News in December
2007 and I said that not only was the
CIA torturing prisoners but that the
torture policy was an official U.S
government policy that was approved at
the very top by the president of the
United States himself
the CIA filed what's called a crimes
report against me the next day with the
justice department the justice
department never stopped investigating
me from December of 2007 until I was
finally arrested in January of 2012. so
to say that this uh that this case is a
result of a name that was found in a in
a an attorney's brief at Guantanamo is
just simply not true so they were
looking for something they were looking
for something to pin on me what I find
most outrageous about your case is had
you been actually
accused of torture of human rights
violations you wouldn't have gone to
jail no
they they would dismiss any accusations
because the US government has classified
everything related to his torture
practices but yet you go to prison
because you talked about it why do you
think this Administration President
Obama who signed an executive order to
stop torture at the very beginning of
his first term why do you think he's
protecting folks from the previous
administration most people don't realize
this but President Obama has surrounded
himself with the same intelligence
advisors who advised President Bush
through most of the first term the CIA
had the same deputy director that bush
had the same director of operations that
bush had John Brennan who's President
Obama's new designee to be the CIA
director and until what a week ago or so
was the deputy National Security adviser
was under President Bush the director of
the national counterterrorism Center and
up to his eyeballs in torture policy so
even though we changed presidents there
was really no change of intelligence
advisors at least not on
counterterrorism John Brennan you
mentioned John Brennan and I want to ask
you about him the future head of the CIA
what kind of a CIA Chief is it going to
be in your opinion I think he's going to
be somebody who will be extremely
aggressive
and who will probably be comfortable
walking on the edge of the law you
worked with him I did I worked with John
Brennan for many years and I know him
pretty well
Mr kirako you yourself supported torture
before you were against it what happened
what changed your position well let me
correct you on that and this is
something that that I think most
Americans missed in my original NBC
interview
I was trying to draw a distinction
between whether torture was right and
wrong or whether it worked I believed it
was wrong and I called it torture and I
said that torture was official policy
that's on the one side on the other side
the CIA had told us internally at the
time that it was working what year was
that that was in 2002 2003 they were
telling us that it was working we now
know from the inspector General's report
that was released in the spring of 2009
that that was a lie that the CIA was
lying even to those of us inside the CIA
and I think it was just to protect
themselves and to protect the policy but
it never worked
did you have a personal experience
related to torture were you personally
involved in torture no thank God I was
never personally involved in torture
when I returned from Pakistan in the
early summer of 2002 where I had been
chief of counterterrorism operations I
was asked by a senior officer in the
cia's counter-terrorist center if I
wanted to be trained in in the use of
these torture techniques and I said no I
had a moral problem with it and I didn't
want to be associated with it there were
14 of us at the time who were made the
offer two of us said no and then one of
us not me the other guy
changed his mind
so I was the only one who was made the
offer who declined because at that time
you already believed that it wouldn't
work I I just thought I didn't know if
it would work I mean they were telling
us it would but I just believed it was
wrong you know at the CIA part of the
cia's culture is to couch all issues in
Shades of Gray you have to be very
comfortable working in morally nebulous
situations or legally nebulous
situations but there are some things
that really are black and white and I
believed that that was a black and white
issue
there's something that I think you will
find interesting and something that I'd
like you to comment on polls by the
American Red Cross show that the
majority of Americans find torture
acceptable sixty percent of young people
agree whereas four years ago torture was
largely condemned in the U.S
how did this become The New Normal what
happened in those four years
I think that many people who told
pollsters in the early or middle part of
the last decade were reacting to
President Bush little by little
President Obama adopted most of
President Bush's counterterrorism
policies and just because he happens to
be Nobel Peace Prize winner Barack Obama
most Americans haven't paid much
attention have just bought it Hussein
Obama I think it's a question of
Education
people need to be informed did Hollywood
have a role to play I think Hollywood
had a role to play I think that Zero
Dark 30 for example did a grave
disservice to counterterrorism Zero Dark
30 perpetuates this Grand lie that
torture led to the to the uh
the killing of Osama bin Laden it's just
simply not true myths often become
history one comedian here said movies it
was about zero dark Theory by the way
it's serious movies is where Americans
learn their history it's true what myths
what other myths do you see being
perpetuated now related to the war on
terror I think one of the great myths
and I I chuckled to myself because it
always seemed so ridiculous to me
was President Bush's statement that they
hate us because we love freedom
I know Al Qaeda I've captured Al-Qaeda
Fighters I've had conversations sitting
across a table like I am with you with
Al Qaeda leaders and I can tell you from
first-hand personal experience that the
reason people take up arms against us is
because of a lack of Education yeah that
I understand but the United States can't
educate the whole world no we can't but
but we can we can help other countries
develop an infrastructure so that they
can educate themselves tell me more more
about your encounters with those what
other Impressions did you have the first
Al-Qaeda fighter I ever caught was a 19
year old boy from Tunisia and the only
reason he went to Afghanistan was
because he had nothing else to do he had
no skills and no way of making a living
and he wanted to get married
so the local Imam said if you want to
make some money you know what you should
do you should go to Afghanistan and make
Jihad against the Americans if you do
that I know somebody who will pay your
family 500 and you can use that for a
dowry and you can you can get a wife
so this kid had nothing against the
United States he had never even really
thought about the United States so from
your experience you saw no ideology I
saw very little you see ideology in some
of the older Fighters some of the
leaders the camp commanders for example
sure there's ideology there but in my
short time in Pakistan I captured 52 Al
Qaeda Fighters I can count on one hand
the number of of people who were real
ideologues who really were there for
Jihad who were really there to kill
Americans three out of 52. the
perception of Guantanamo II has gone a
long way since 2008 when he was a
burning and a highly controversial issue
most recently you know the state
department has shut down the office that
was working to shut down the Guantanamo
prison
is that this administration's way of
saying
forget about Guantanamo let's move on I
think it is
I think it is again where's the outrage
the American people really don't care if
Guantanamo is open or closed this
Administration it appears decided not to
bother about interrogations Guantanamo
and prisoners and all that and just to
bomb whoever seems suspicious with
drones what do you think about this
administration's no prisoners policy
we we find ourselves murdering people in
many cases children with no evidence
whatsoever that they're involved in any
criminal or terrorist activity
and what this does is it encourages
other people to take up arms against us
John Brennan the architect of the Drone
program basically and it was last year I
think
when he claimed that U.S drone strikes
caused no civilian deaths in Pakistan
over the prior year which was an
outright Lie by so many accounts do you
think we're going to see more
transparency with regards to drones with
John Brennan at the Helm of the CIA no
no I don't
um with John Brennan
secrecy is the key word
unless of course you know he chooses to
leak for the benefit of the
administration what did you expect
decided to go public to come clean on on
torture at the CIA I mean your wife
worked at the CIA and she was fired
because of you you're a father of five
and you're going to prison what future
did you envision for yourself five years
ago
I didn't Envision prison in my future
five years ago I expected there to be a
national debate on whether or not we
wanted to use torture as an official U.S
policy now I'm very happy proud actually
that I played a role in that debate and
now the the law of the land is that
torture is illegal I'm very proud of
that I frankly didn't expect that the
government would would
go after me so relentlessly I stood in
the snow for two hours to vote for
president Obama I really believed that
this was positive change I believed that
he deserved that Nobel Peace Prize only
because I expected things to change so
dramatically at the beginning of his
first term
so no I never believed I would be going
to prison under a President Obama never
that's been I think my biggest
disappointment
but you haven't seen a dramatic change I
haven't seen any change
no he stopped torture he stopped torture
sure but in terms of counter-terrorism
policy I think the Obama Administration
is largely an extension of the Bush
Administration
Mr kiriaku thank you for the interview I
wish you all the best thanks very much
for having me